Acknowledgments

I would like to Forrest Wang for the best passenger experience I have ever had, tandem drifting around Virginia International Raceway in his Formula D race car. Dave Hendrickson kindly offered me a co-driver seat in his desert racer for the Caliente 250, and this opened doors to interesting conversations with racers Journee Richardson and Victoria Hazelwood, whom I also thank. Barron Wright introduced me to the hare scramble scene in central Virginia, and once showed up at my house late at night after a heavy snowfall, on a dirt bike, towing his young son behind him on a sled. I thank Matt Linkous and Darryl Allen for stopping and waiting for me to catch up on many trail rides through the Blue Ridge Mountains.

Thanks to Charles “Chas” Martin for initiating me, as a teenager, into the rich world of the mechanic. In doing so, he showed me an order of value that was more appealing to me than the prevailing one. The members of Shop Talk Forums on the internet have taught me most of what I know about air-cooled Volkswagens; thanks to everyone for sharing their hard-won knowledge.

The Specialty Equipment Manufacturer’s Association (SEMA) was the first institution to give me a platform for exploring “the psychology of vehicle customization.” Thanks to Zane Clark for the invitation to speak at SEMA 2017. At the opposite end of the spectrum, as far from Las Vegas as one can get, Mathieu Flonneau invited me to give a talk at the Sorbonne, “Managing Traffic: Three Rival Versions of Rationality.” I would like to thank Flonneau, Jean-Pierre Dupuy and the other attendees for their comments in the resulting seminar, held under the auspices of LabEx EHNE at the International Social Science Council in Paris in April, 2018. I presented the same material in Montreal, at a conference of the International Association for the History of Traffic, Transport and Mobility, and thank the participants for their criticisms. The Center for the Humanities and Social Change at the University of California, Santa Barbara, hosted a lecture and two seminars in which the ideas in this book were subject to scrutiny from a variety of disciplines. Thanks to Tom Carlson for arranging that, and for his own thoughtful engagement with the book.

The Institute for Advanced Studies in Culture at the University of Virginia has been an unflagging source of support and intellectual fellowship, a rare space for truly open inquiry. They hosted a workshop to discuss this project at an early stage of its development. I would like to thank Ann Brach, Director of Technical Activities for the Transportation Research Board of The National Academies of Sciences for driving down from Washington to participate, and for her invaluable comments. At this workshop, Jackson Lears alerted me to the “vitalist tradition” as a useful point of orientation for thinking about the value of risk. I also got very helpful comments from Joe Davis, Peter Norton, Jay Tolson, Ari Schulman, and Garnette Cadogan.

Matt Feeney and Matt Frost, my companions in text message samizdat, have helped keep the pleasure of thinking alive for me. Thanks to Beth Crawford for teaching rats to drive, for countless fascinating conversations about the role of the body in cognition, and for accompanying me on the long road of writing this and previous books. Thanks to Mario and Luigi for persevering when the Fruit Loop was so close, and yet so far.

I want to thank the man who filled my jugs with water when I was broken down in rural California in the dead of night, and the man who gave me fifty dollars (in exchange for a cursed Jeepster) the next day, to cover the train ride home. Thanks to Troy, the gangster who terrorized my childhood neighborhood, for trying to jump over ten garbage cans on his BMX bike. In doing so, he recalibrated my sense of what human beings are capable of, and what they might be willing to risk in the attempt. Thanks to my father, Frank S. Crawford, for chasing down the lowland bicycle thieves in an excellent episode of vigilante justice, conducted in style from behind the wheel of a Ford Fairlane convertible with his freak flag flying in the wind. Thanks to the taxi drivers of London, for their erudition and gentlemanliness. To whoever laid out Route 9 through the Santa Cruz mountains. To my daughters, G and J, for insisting that I take the twisty road on the way home from their preschool, squealing “go faster!”

Breaking Down

1972 Jeepster Commando

I ordered another cup of coffee, though I had no intention of drinking it. It seemed the thing to do, since I was taking up real estate at the counter. I was in a diner off Highway 101 in San Miguel, not quite a town but a “census-designated place” in central California, bone tired and wondering what the hell I was going to do. It must have been around two in the morning. January 1987. The waitress likely wasn’t used to seeing a twenty-one-year-old nursing a tab at such an hour; she lingered at my stool in a way that seemed to invite words. So I asked her if the local cops were likely to come and roust me, if I were to be found sleeping in my truck.

“Where you headed?”

“Nowhere, fast.” I liked the sound of that; I’d been rehearsing it.

I explained my situation. She said there was a junkyard about a mile down the frontage road.

“Really?” A warm trickle of hope spread through my limbs, better than any amount of her sour coffee.

“And don’t worry about cops. CHP is the only police through here.” But that issue was now moot; I no longer felt the need for sleep. The junkyard would likely open in another six hours.

It had been five hours since my night took a bad turn. I was southbound on 101 in my 1972 Jeepster when a sickening sound from the engine bay—a rapid DAT DAT DAT DAT DAT—announced that Plan A was out the window. As soon as I heard the sound I recalled a certain detail, one of a hundred on a mental to-do list that was a little too haphazard. This one concerned the mounting of the radiator: two bolts rather than four, as I now remembered, one of which didn’t quite seem to match the threads of the nut that I had nonetheless jammed onto it, just to hold the radiator in place “for the time being” as I finished up an engine swap. That time was no longer being.

I had bought the Jeep the previous summer, after being charmed by a friend’s 1964 International Harvester Scout. Four of us had taken it on a camping trip in the Sierras, a post–high school reunion the highlights of which included an ice-cold waterfall, sleeping under the stars on a massive slab of upturned granite, and the giddy pleasure of bouncing along a rutted trail in four-wheel drive, wondering if various streams were too deep to cross in a vehicle. Having four able-bodied youths to push and pull and dig, if need be, provided a little insurance. Together we might have been able to muster half a horsepower! But the little four-cylinder Scout with the manually locking front hubs handled it all with aplomb. It wasn’t lifted, it had skinny little tires and a soft suspension: perfect. Brian had paid $800 for it. It was painted desert tan.

The closest equivalent I was able to find, scouring Auto Trader for the Bay Area (a publication of classified ads you could buy at convenience stores) was a 1972 Jeepster Commando, one of the early progenitors of what would soon become the SUV. It was baby blue, lifted, with a removable hard top and no roll bar. I took the top off immediately. Cruising around in the open air, perched atop an obviously unstable death trap, rowing through the gears frequently due to the low-revving engine (it had a manual four-speed mated to a straight-six), I felt like a devilish character in some adventure story. (The young male is given to motorized self-dramatization.) I felt charismatic through no merit of my own—other than having had the inspiration to seek this thing out.

But the story took a bad turn on the first page. The day after I bought it, I was doing a little nighttime four-wheeling (at a construction site, if you must know—I’m not proud of this) in San Francisco when the motor cut out. As I would discover after having it towed back to my place in Berkeley, a worn motor mount had allowed the engine to bounce around to the point that the oil filter got punctured by the motor mount, and there was no oil pressure warning light. The motor was fried.

I purchased an engine out of a different model of Jeep from a junkyard, and did the swap out on the street in front of my dad’s house. It took weeks. Every couple of days I had to push the truck along the street to a different spot to satisfy a very zealous parking enforcer named Ortega who already had it in for me, based on my history of inoperable vehicles. A few days after I finished the engine swap, the truck got stolen in broad daylight, on Bancroft Way. Some months later the cops found the cursed thing, and this trip to Santa Barbara was my first real excursion in it.

Upon hearing the aforementioned DAT DAT DAT, I pulled to the shoulder of the road and popped the hood. I had no flashlight. But, feeling with my hands, it was clear that the radiator had indeed fallen from its mount. Into the fan. Coolant was everywhere, to judge from the sweet smell and slippery wetness. I rooted around in the back, which was full of stuff: I was on my way from Berkeley back to Santa Barbara for the winter term at UCSB. I found a coat hanger and some lineman’s pliers, and I wire-tied the radiator up out of the way of the fan. The question, now, was how much coolant I had lost. And at what rate would it leak out when I started the motor up again? There was no washer fluid in the reservoir. I regretted having stopped to urinate an hour earlier: more precious fluid to use in a pinch.

I had no water in the truck, but I considered carefully which objects could be turned to use as containers. I had a couple of quarts of oil that might have to be sacrificed on the roadside—not the least of the environmental sins I had committed in the course of six years of dealing with fucked-up old cars. And I had a large stainless steel stockpot that I had been using for cliffside fires and as a makeshift barbeque on surf trips down the coast.

But where to find water? The road was pitch-dark. I hadn’t passed an exit for maybe fifteen miles, and there was no sign of any exit ahead. I was somewhere near the border between Monterey County and San Luis Obispo County, the heart of rural central California: cattle, lettuce, strawberries, garlic. It was a moonless night; I could not see my own feet on the ground. But I could see a single light off in the distance to the east. Whatever lay between me and the light was invisible. It wasn’t the sort of light that beckoned; the color of it was industrial looking, not commercial. It couldn’t be a porch light.

I gathered my containers, crossed the highway, and scrambled blindly down an embankment. The sandy terrain was pocked with the fragrant chaparral of the inland coast. I crossed a flat and relatively even area; it seemed to be a dry riverbed. When the light was out of view, I could reckon my direction only by my general sense that the ups and downs of the terrain ran parallel to the highway. Several times I fell hard into what seemed like artificial trenches, very sudden and crisply edged, two or three feet deep. I came to a two-lane road, and now I could see the source of harsh white light that had been my pole star. It was above a door, the only entrance visible in a small compound of corrugated metal buildings, surrounded by a chain-link fence. It was a serious fence, maybe twelve feet high and angled outward at the top. I scanned the building, as much of it as I could see by the light, and didn’t see any hose or spigot.

I doubted there was a soul in the vicinity. And in any case, I have a real aversion to making a nuisance of myself. I stood there for five minutes thinking, “Oh well.” The voice of defeat. But then I thought of the overland odyssey of getting to this damn light; I was pretty well invested at this point. What the hell. I started yelling from the fenced perimeter. Nothing. I yelled some more. Still nothing. I was about to turn around and head back toward the highway when the door opened. Somebody was shining a flashlight at me.

“Hey. Hi. Sorry to get you up. I’m looking for some water,” I said, loudly but not yelling. There was no response. But after another ten seconds a floodlight came on, and now I could see the backlit silhouette of a man walking toward me. Only when he got right up to the fence could I see his face. I told him my situation, and also asked how far it was to the next town south.

“How’d you get here?”

I pointed over my shoulder with my thumb. “Through there.”

He paused and seemed to think. Yes, he would fill my containers. Emboldened, I asked if maybe he had some better containers he would be willing to part with. He didn’t think so. He told me to walk twenty yards down the fence line; there was a gate there. He opened the gate, took my containers, and brought them back full after ten minutes. The next exit was Camp Roberts, a military base. After that, he wasn’t sure. I asked him if he knew what the deal was with the trenches that I kept falling into.

“Those are tank tracks. This area is used for tank training and live-fire exercises.”

“Oh.”

Now I had a couple of armfuls of water, and I set off the way I had come. The first problem was that I had no light to guide me on the return. The second problem was sloshing. I was glad it was a warm night (for January) because I was getting pretty wet. I went slowly, taking smaller and more tentative steps than before, trying to visualize the terrain. I imagined how I might show up in a pair of night vision binoculars from the turret of a tank—I made for an odd thermal picture, I guessed, with my pot of cold water hugged to my warm torso, doing what must have looked like a crane dance of delicate marsh steps.

By the time I reached 101 and found my truck in the darkness, I had two quarts plus about two-thirds of a stockpot of water. I set the water down, opened the cab, and sat down, sweating. It was quiet. The moon was now rising, off to the southeast. I felt the momentary ease that comes with having accomplished something by force of will and physical exertion. I also felt pleased that I had prevailed over my inhibition to ask another human being to render aid, which was the most uncomfortable part. The arduous path by which I had arrived at that chain-link fence made it easier. I wasn’t waving a handkerchief on the side of the road like some helpless incompetent. I had earned the right to ask that man for water, and he gave me water.

I took the cap off the radiator, which had long since cooled. I hoisted the stockpot up high (the Jeepster was lifted), feeling a burn in my shoulders. I rested it on the valve cover of the straight-six and positioned my body so as not to block the bit of moonlight that now made it possible to make out the features of the engine bay. I carefully tipped the stockpot over the mouth of the radiator and poured. For the first several seconds my aim was approximate, and the water splashed around, but now I had a good pour going, nice and slow. However, the sound of water hitting the ground didn’t decrease. It seemed to increase. It was now a gush that sounded about equal to the rate at which I was pouring water in. I kept pouring, grimly, because there was nothing else to do with this goddamn water.

Only now did I recall that the entire excursion of the last two hours had been prompted by a mere hypothesis, a hope that the radiator was not completely destroyed. When a situation looks grim, but also you’re not sure exactly how things stand, you form theories that are attractive not because they are the most plausible but because they give you something to do, and doing something is the only way not to be crushed by miasmic uncertainty and despair. Fetching water had given me a purpose. As so often happens for mortals like us, it turned out to be a pointless purpose. But string enough of these together and you’ve got yourself a life, of sorts. We are playthings of the gods, and to provide amusement is not nothing.

That is easy to say now, but at the moment I wasn’t feeling so philosophical. When you work on cars, you come to identify with them. It’s all about their needs. You put yourself in the service of these needs. Well, guess what, I got needs too. I need to get the hell out of here, Jeepster. Maybe you are disposable.

It was time to hit the road, heat exchange be damned. I got back in, started the motor, and drove. I’d like to say I drove her like a desperado, but no, I was looking at her temperature gauge the whole time. The needle was moving so fast I could see it sweep, like a second hand. After about two miles it was into the red. I pulled over and shut off the motor. Let’s not talk.

I waited maybe twenty minutes and did another couple of miles. After a few of these short hops I had passed the Camp Roberts exit, which did not look the least bit hospitable, and made it to San Miguel, where I pulled into the parking lot of the diner. The motor dieseled on for a good fifteen seconds after I turned off the ignition as the red-hot combustion chambers continued to ignite stray bits of hydrocarbon sucked past the throttle plate in a rattling chain reaction that announced the arrival of a long-term counter sitter. Embarrassing.

Sometime around eight in the morning I picked my head up off my folded-up jacket at a booth in the diner, got in the truck, and drove the mile to the junkyard. I told the owner I had seventeen dollars. He took a long look at me, forming some kind of judgment. Then he let me root around in a pile of radiators. The trick was to find one that had an inlet on the top right and an outlet on the bottom left, with the same hose diameter as the original, and with dimensions that would fit in the available space. Mounting points would have to be improvised. The only viable candidate was from a compact car. I figured it would cool well enough to get me to Santa Barbara. In retrospect, this was a case of what the psychologists call “motivated reasoning.” I wanted it to be true, and the physics major in me backed that wish up. Physicists, when they talk about actual things at all (as opposed to frictionless surfaces and perfect vacuums), register only “order of magnitude” differences. Anything less is too trivial to be of any theoretical interest. This radiator was smaller by about a factor of two. Trivial.

I got the thing jerry-rigged into my truck. I was absolutely filthy, but happy, and I took off confidently down the frontage road toward the next entrance ramp. Before I even got onto 101, the temperature gauge was spiking. I saw it but decided it was an anomaly. Maybe there was an air bubble in the system and it would work its way out. Or something. I pulled onto 101 going maybe forty miles per hour in a state of willful, desperate theorizing, wishing the temperature away. After another mile reality was becoming too insistent to deny. I was refuted, utterly.

I nursed it along to the next exit and pulled into the parking lot of the first establishment, a motel. I got out, sat down on the curb with my arms propped up on my knees, and was still. I was done. I had nothing left of will, ideas, or cash. The Jeepster was well and truly cursed, and I was ready to walk away from it: just start walking down Highway 101 like a hobo. I looked the part, certainly.

A funny thing happened as I sat there: my despair opened up, or it cleared the way for a different feeling. I felt free. Maybe I would take a job and live here in San Miguel for a spell. Maybe I would wander the hills and speak to crows. Maybe some voluptuous single mom would take me in and make me soup. I was healthy, I was capable, and I knew how to talk to strangers.

Looking back on that moment now, I can see that it was the freedom of faith—faith in my own powers, but also faith that the world was basically hospitable, if I threw myself into it with trust.

Just as this feeling of lightness and strength was spreading through my body, the owner of the motel came out and said, “Can I help you?”

Feeling magnanimous, I nodded behind me and said, “You want a Jeepster?”

He looked over at it. “Not especially. How much?”

“How much is a train ticket back to Oakland?”

“Probably fifty dollars.”

“That’s how much.”

He drove me to Paso Robles. I took the next Amtrak north. There I retrieved a different piece of shit: a 1963 VW bus that was rotting in my father’s driveway. I dropped the motor, put in a new clutch, and headed once again for Santa Barbara.

The steering wheel is nearly horizontal in those things, and huge. The effect is that you really do feel like you’re driving a bus, steering hand over hand in a great looping motion around town as the expanse of unsupported sheet metal amplifies the mechanical noises like a drum. The steering wheel also makes a good perch on long trips; you can lean your forearms on it and relax. With your head inches from the flat windshield, you feel like a bow spirit. There is nothing in front of you but a piece of plate glass. Hunched over this way is a good position in which to give yourself over to reverie as the farms and hills of Central California go by at an unhurried, Volkswagen pace. Sometimes a car seems not simply to move you through the world, but to put you into the world more thoroughly.

Project Rat Rod

Cognitive psychologist L. Elizabeth Crawford wondered if she could teach rats to drive. It was a question that arose out of a couple of ingredients. The first was her professional interest in the way our bodily locomotion through the environment affects such capacities as spatial memory. The second was more fortuitous: she had a sabbatical year during which she got into tinkering with electronics, combining sensors and actuators to do weird things just for the hell of it. (A keeper of chickens in a predator-rich neighborhood, she rigged up her chicken coop to detect when a hen had laid an egg, and to then send out a tweet consisting, appropriately enough, of the single word “tweet!”) Around this time her husband was starting work on a book about driving, and the two of them had conversations that ranged from “embodied cognition” to animal intelligence; from human-machine interface and the peculiar pleasures of driving a car to the sometimes mentally enervating effects of automation. The connections between bodily skills and other forms of intelligence suggested fertile questions about culture and technology.

So. Could rats be taught to drive?

Crawford didn’t know much about rats but Kelly Lambert, her colleague in the psychology department at the University of Richmond, did, so the two of them teamed up. According to Lambert, we have no idea what rats are capable of because rat research has always been conducted in a highly controlled lab environment, the point of which is to study the effect of one variable and eliminate confounding variables as much as possible. But it is precisely the richness of an animal’s environment that calls forth its evolved capacities, many of which depend on a process of development (during the rat’s own lifetime) in a natural setting no less than the selection pressures that have shaped the species over generations. She told me researchers have never investigated the question of skills with their furry subjects, as opposed to their ability to do simple, discrete tasks such as nosing a button to release a treat in response to some stimulus. Yet they are known to be very intelligent animals. Crawford wondered: could they be taught to find their way through the world by making use of a truly alien mode of locomotion? This would require learning a whole new set of “motor skills” and integrating these skills with their map of the world in a new way, successfully enough to get where they want to go. To get a Fruit Loop, as in previous experiments in Lambert’s lab. But to do it in style, with a nice set of wheels.

Let us digress for just a moment to note a classic experiment that explored the role of movement in perception, and specifically the role of self-motion, as opposed to being transported around passively. Ten pairs of kittens were reared in the dark, except for three hours per day that each pair spent in a carousel apparatus that allowed one of them to move freely, while the other was carried passively by the movements of the first. The active kitten could move up, down, away from, or toward the center of the carousel, as well as rotate in epicycles at the periphery of the carousel’s radius. The kittens could not see each other, and the surrounding environment was contrived so that both kittens received identical visual stimulation as they moved around; the only difference was that one moved itself, the other was passively carried. The active kittens developed normally; the passive kittens failed to develop visually guided paw placement, avoidance of a visual cliff, a blink response to quickly approaching objects, or visual pursuit of a moving object.

These finding were the tip of an iceberg that became “embodied cognition,” now a prominent research program in psychology. As Alva Noë puts it, “When we perceive, we perceive in an idiom of possibilities for movement.” Further, our perception of these possibilities depends on what kind of tools we use to get around, and a corresponding skill set.[1]

Crawford’s first order of business was to build a rat car, in what historians will surely regard as the pioneering attempt at “rat-machine interface” design (how this differs from getting a rat to simply press a button, we will get to shortly). She went to Radio Shack and got a cheap radio-controlled car, cannibalized the chassis and motors, then made an enclosure consisting of a transparent cashew container (the really giant ones you get from Costco) with some windows cut out of it to allow the rat olfactory connection to the environment. She made a control mechanism using the Arduino platform favored by tinkerers. I am proud to say I had the honor of welding up a rat-friendly joystick housing for an early prototype. It turns out rats don’t like joysticks. (Or at least, Mario and Luigi didn’t like my joystick.) They prefer separate left, right, and straight-ahead controls. In the current iteration of the rat rod (as I insist on calling it), Crawford is using conductive bars that the rats grab with their little mitts, closing a circuit.[2]

It took about a year of prototype development for Crawford and Lambert to get the basic rat ergonomics worked out, and to fine-tune some other elements of the experimental design. For example, because rats use smell to find their way as much as sight, and Fruit Loops don’t have much aroma, various smelly substances were put adjacent to the Fruit Loop. As it turns out, a wet tea bag is just the ticket.

More significant, this research required a leap of faith to embark on a long-term program of rat driver’s ed. Nothing remotely like this had been tried. There is a hundred years of research based on teaching rats to do various things by inducing a “conditioned response.” Essentially, the rat is treated as a stimulus-response machine that can be trained to display a certain range of behaviors.

Crawford, alive with an infectious geeky charisma, stood in her kitchen one morning in April 2019 and explained to me how this project differs. The initial task that the rats needed to learn was simply to press on a bar to make the car drive straight ahead to where a Fruit Loop awaited them. Their success at this, which came quickly, essentially replicated the kind of training that lab rats have long been subject to. This early training served to familiarize the rats with the car, get them comfortable with the setting, and acquaint them with particular people—generally undergrads in white lab coats.

The next task the rats needed to learn was to press on a bar located to their right to make the car simply pivot to the right, where a Fruit Loop was to be had. This task too was easily learned, and in line with the kind of tasks traditionally demanded of lab rats. (The rats were never taught to turn left, and the significance of this will become clear shortly.) These basic competencies became the scaffold on which the next stage of training would be built.

The car was placed at the far end of the driving arena from the Fruit Loop, and pointed in the wrong direction. After a protracted period of trial and error lasting months, in the course of which the researchers permitted the rats to run into walls, get stuck and generally frustrated, something remarkable happened. Having taught themselves to turn left, the rats began to find their way, navigating to the Fruit Loop in a zigzagging trajectory, overshooting with their steering inputs and forward movements and then correcting course. Crawford explained to me how this task is different in kind from the previous ones. First, it is not simply more difficult, in the sense of requiring some new dexterity of an unaccustomed kind. What the final version of the driving task does is expand the problem space that the rat needs to solve. In fact, there is literally an infinite number of trajectories that could be taken to get from the starting point and initial orientation of the car to the location and orientation that allows the rat to get the Fruit Loop. After each zig, the rat needs to zag in response to the new situation. This is just what we do on a much finer temporal and spatial scale on foot (the subtle course correction that all animals engage in subconsciously). This open problem space resembles that of an animal’s natural environment, as opposed to a laboratory setting contrived to elicit a particular behavior. But unlike the rat’s usual reliance on its own bodily equipment for solving the problem, here its intention has to pass through a strange machine.

To watch the researchers’ videos of rats unquestionably driving, with increasing fluidity, is astonishing.[3] Crawford believes it is the first instance of genuine tool use by rats, if by that we mean the flexible use of an instrument in response to some evolving situation, in a feedback loop of perception and action that crafts the ongoing development of the situation toward some goal of the agent. That is, skill. The car becomes a kind of prosthetic, an extension of the rat’s body, in the same way that the limbs of a toddler, initially alien and awkward, may be understood as prosthetics of the brain that gradually get integrated with the brain in the course of development. Thus does an embodied being become competent, in ways specific to its environmental niche. Our limbs and hands and, later, various tools that we become skilled in using no longer feel like prosthetics. They fade into the background and become transparent, that is, unobtrusive conduits for both action and perception.

I believe some clues for the significance of the Crawford-Lambert rat driving project for human culture, including driving, may be found in earlier work by Lambert. In experiments on both rats and people, she explored what she calls “effort-driven rewards.”[4] Lambert found that “movement—and especially hand movements that lead to desired outcomes—plays a key role in both preventing the onset of and building resilience against depression and other emotional disorders. Furthermore, we are predisposed to preferring hand movements that our ancestors needed for survival—those necessary for nurturing, cleaning, cooking, grooming, building shelter and farming.” Lambert theorizes that the enormous increase in rates of anxiety and depression over the last few decades may be due in part to our disengagement from the basic tasks of securing our own bodily needs, and “all the complexity of movement and thought processes” such tasks require of us.

“The decreased brain activation associated with increasingly effortless-driven rewards may, over time, diminish your perception of control over your environment and increase your vulnerability to mental illnesses such as depression . . . . Anything that lets us see a clear connection between effort and consequence—and that helps us feel in control of a challenging situation—is a kind of mental vitamin that helps build resilience and provides a buffer against depression.” Closely connected to her work on effort-driven rewards, Lambert found that rats who enjoyed an “enriched environment” more closely resembling the natural world, with its problems to solve, were more persistent in solving problems and less prone to get stressed out, compared to rats kept in standard lab enclosures. In the rat driving study, Crawford and Lambert found that rats raised in an enriched environment learned to drive more readily, and that rats who drove themselves had a stress hormone response different from that of the rats who were passively driven. It is a difference that is associated with lower anxiety in humans.

As I see it, this work has a clear upshot for human beings. As we grapple with the challenges of automation, we may want to arrange our own environment like that of the happy rats, rather than the overdetermined world of their anxious counterparts. Of course, we do not simply live in the natural environment. But the built environment of technology and cultural practices can likewise be rich enough that it demands the use of our full repertoire of intelligence. Flourishing—that of rats and humans alike—seems to require an environment with “open problem spaces” that elicit the kinds of bodily and mental engagement bequeathed us by evolution and cultural development. These exquisitely honed human capacities include the glorious, century-long development of the automobile, that astonishing tool, and the social intelligence that we have brought to bear on the problem of sharing the road together. If instead we put ourselves in a Plexiglas enclosure in which all our most basic needs are met, we will have nobody but ourselves to blame if we begin to feel like standard lab rats in a massive laboratory of social engineering. We would be safer that way, no doubt. But remember, all rats die. Not every rat lives.